What is your name?
你的名字是？
Mioh Kofune.
小舟泠
When were you born? How?
你是在什么时候 由谁生出来的
Yesterday. Mother scanned Mioh at the wake.
昨天守灵时 妈妈扫描了泠
Later that night...
当天深夜里
I was born in the cave.
我在那个洞窟中诞生了
When you say "Mother," you mean Heine in Shiori's body?
你口中的妈妈 是指变成诗织样貌的波稻吧？
Yes.
嗯
Did you cut the brakes in Mio's bicycle?
是你弄坏了泠自行车上的刹车吗
To kill me?
为了杀我？
Not necessarily. It was just more convenient if you were in the hospital.
没死也没关系 只要让你受伤 去了医院 就容易下手了
It's more convenient to kill Mio in the hospital and take her place?
你是说在医院里杀了泠之后 可以更方便地取代她吗
Yes, since Dr. Hishigata is an ally of the shadows.
是 因为菱形医生是站在影子这边的
Was that Heine's order?
这是波稻的命令吗
No, I just wanted to do that. But I failed.
不 这是我自己想做的事 但失败了
I didn't know that she was making Mio's shadow.
没人告诉过我要制造泠的影子的事
Don't worry, Tokiko. Now I don't even know why I wanted to kill her.
放心吧 朱鹭子 现在我已经不知道 当初为什么要杀她了
Heine created you to find Ushio's shadow.
波稻是为了找潮姐姐的影子 才把你生出来的吧
She is a traitor, after all.
因为她是背叛者
I can't copy people. Can you?
我无法复制人 你能吗
There are two types of copying.
复制有两种类型
Taking the form of the person we copy, or giving birth to a new shadow.
拍摄自己身体的变身 以及让身体分裂生出新影子的分娩
Giving birth?
分娩？
We children can give birth to a new shadow only once.
我们这些孩子只能分娩一次人的影子
"Children"?
孩子？
Heine can give birth as many times as she wants,
波稻可以生产无数次
but since she has become weak, it's no longer easy for her.
但因为她身体虚弱 现在也无法轻易做到了
Shadows at the grandchild level cannot give birth.
由孩子生出的孙子一代没有分娩能力
Shadows can transform multiple times.
变身的话 只要是影子 就可以变身无数次
Regardless of which type of copy we are,
不过不管是分娩还是变身
we have one week to erase the original, or we turn into mud and disappear.
复制了人就要在一周内将原型消除 否则就会变成泥而消失
I have six more days to live, although I don't really care.
我也只剩下六天的生命 但现在我已经觉得不在乎了
That's all I know.
大概就是这些了
Sorry, Shinpei. I don't have much useful information.
抱歉 小慎 没提供多少有用的情报
Ah, no...
没关系的
Y-You don't need to apologize!
别这么说 你不用道歉的
Hey, that's a shadow, Sou.
喂 她可是影子啊 窗
What? Ah, but...
什么 可是…
-Sou?
-窗？
Ah, darn it! This is confusing.
可恶 我脑子有点乱了
Heine needs to consume a lot of people for her to be revived.
波稻为了复活 需要食用大量的人类
She's giving birth to build an army for that.
分娩就是为了这个目的而制造军队
Father and I tried to revive Heine for Mother.
我和爸爸为了妈妈 想让波稻复活
We thought she needed the meals for that purpose...
我以为是为了这个目的而进食 但并不是这样
but they had a different objective.
那些家伙有其他目的
And the old man knew everything?
还说爸爸对这一切都是知情的
Unbelievable. He doesn't care if we all die.
开什么玩笑 他根本不在乎我们的生死吗
Father.
爸爸他…
It's hard to take it in, but Dr. Hishigata must know Heine's true objective.
虽然还有很多地方没搞清楚 但菱形医生应该知道波稻真正的目的
I'm meeting him tonight at 10 p.m.
我和我爸约好了今晚10点见面
Okay, then we know what to do next.
好 那下一个目的地就决定了
We're going to the Hishigata Clinic.
去菱形医院
It's so itchy! There are so many mosquitoes here!
好痒啊 这里好多蚊子
Protect Mio.
保护好泠
Is that an order?
这是命令？
I don't know if it's an order... Uh, I guess it is.
命令啊…嗯 也算是命令吧
Shinpei, are you afraid of me? You're so far away.
小慎 你怕我吗 怎么离这么远
I guess I'd be lying if I said no.
这个嘛 说不害怕是假的
You killed me over and over, you know.
我可是被你杀了好几次的
That was in another world. I haven't killed anyone yet.
你说的是其他世界的我吧？ 我还没杀过人哦
Can I ask you something too?
我可以问你个问题吗
Did you have a girlfriend in Tokyo?
你在东京有女朋友了吗
-A girl-- -Girlfriend?
-女朋友？
W-What are you asking him?
你这问的是什么问题啦
He sometimes has a Tokyo accent. It's totally suspicious. Is it not?
小慎时不时会说普通话 这很可疑 你不觉得吗
I don't have a girlfriend.
没有女朋友
People just don't understand the Wakayama dialect in Tokyo.
因为在东京大家都听不懂和歌山话嘛
I try to blend in with the locals.
我这是入乡随俗
Have you ever wondered why I don't call you "Brother"?
不过小慎你有没有想过 为什么我不管你叫哥哥呢
Listen. I'll follow your order and protect Mio.
我会听你的命令保护好泠的
But you're the only one who can really protect Mio.
不过啊 真正能保护泠的人 只有小慎你哦
I-I don't know what she's talking about!
不懂你在说什么 干什么啦
Let's just go, Shinpei!
好了 快走吧 小慎
It's open.
门没锁
What's going on? Everything in our house is gone.
怎么回事 家里的东西都不见了
Our rooms are empty too. Desks, closets, beds, everything.
哥哥和我的房间也搬空了 桌子 衣柜和床 全都没了
Ms. Nagumo?
南云老师 这是…
Yes.
嗯
There are no human stains. It seems that only things were erased.
幸好不是人的痕迹 被消除的只是家具而已
Was there anything that they didn't want us to see?
是不是有什么东西不能被我们看见
Although it seems like they erased everything.
不过感觉像是看到什么就消除什么
They had to hide something, but didn't know where it was.
明知道对方是在隐藏什么 却不清楚位置在哪里
That's my impression.
这就是我的感觉
This has to be my old man! That's why he's not here.
一定是爸爸干的 他人不在这里就是最好的证据
Our mother is gone too. What the hell is happening?
妈妈也不在 到底是怎么回事啊 可恶
Shinpei!
慎平
You felt a shadow over here, didn't you, Ushioh?
是从这里开始 感觉到影子的气息吧 潮
Yes.
嗯
Ow! Don't squeeze so hard! It cuts off the blood flow. You scared?
好痛 怎么突然变紧了 血液没法流通 是因为害怕吗
O-Of course, I'm scared! I hate hospitals at night...
当然害怕 我最怕晚上的医院了
I hear something.
有声音
It's not coming. What's that sound?
没反应 这声音是…
Is something stuck in the door at the basement level?
下面那一层有什么东西卡住了电梯门
Bullet holes.
弹痕
It looks like there was a fight here.
有打斗过的痕迹
Be careful. I sense shadows below us.
大家小心 影子就在这下面
What's in the basement?
地下是什么地方
The morgue.
是太平间
The morgue?
太平间？
It's fine.
没事的
The only thing down there is Ushio's body that Father didn't cremate.
现在那里只有父亲替换掉的 潮姐姐你的遗体
Is that really the issue?
问题在这里吗
Feeling fear shows that
感觉到害怕是因为 身体的生存本能在正常发挥作用
It's nothing to be embarrassed about.
不是什么丢人的事
Shadows are scarier than ghosts. Brace yourselves.
影子可比鬼可怕多了 别掉以轻心
That's our mother's wheelchair. Why is it here?
妈妈的轮椅为什么会在这里
Behind you!
后面
MORGUE
太平间
Did you see their face?
看到脸了吗
No.
没
T-There's nothing here.
什么都没有
Seriously? I had no idea this place was under our house.
不是吧 我家地下竟然有这种地方
It's gone.
不见了
Ushio's body was here?
潮的遗体之前放在这里？
Yes. Ushioh can recover if she scans the original, right?
是 只要扫描原型 潮姐姐就能恢复吧
He must have decided it was best not to leave it here until tomorrow.
之前我们以为 在明天之前放在这里 是最为妥当的
Want to restart?
要重来一次吗
No, let's keep going. We need to find Sou's parents.
不 我们继续前进 必须找到窗的父母
Understood.
我知道了
What's this passage, Tokiko?
朱鹭子 这条路是？
It connects to Hiruko's grotto.
直通蛭子洞的参道
There was an entrance here.
这里也有入口吗
We use it to bring meals to Heine.
我们通过这条路 把食物运送到波稻的卧室
It's a different route than the old path from the old clinic.
和旧医院楼那条古旧的路是分开的吧
I feel a subtle presence of a shadow. The one from earlier must've gone in here.
我也感觉到一些影子的气息 刚才的影子是从这里跑到深处去了吧
It's close. It's right there.
很接近了 各位 就在眼前了
Mother?
妈妈？
What is happening?
到底发生了什么事
Don't shoot! Please don't shoot her!
别开枪 先别开枪
But your father will die!
可是你爸就快被杀掉了
Ushioh!
潮
It's okay, Sou. I'll bring her back.
放心吧 窗 我会让她恢复的
Father!
爸爸
He's not breathing.
没呼吸了
Let me!
换我来
Come on, don't die on me.
爸 你不能死
Don't go without explaining yourself. Wake up, old man!
你要是就这样死了 我绝不会原谅你 给我醒过来 臭老头
Sou?
窗吗
Stop keeping secrets. We're family.
别再有所隐瞒了 我们不是一家人吗
How is Chitose... your mother?
千登势呢 你妈呢
I cut her link with Heine. She'll wake up soon.
我切断了她与波稻的联系 再过一会儿就会醒了
I see. I never thought...
是吗 你们…
you'd reach this point so soon.
居然已经查到这一步了
So Heine must've thought that I'd talk.
所以波稻那女的 才会以为是我说出去的
No point in hiding anything. We can just copy your data.
隐瞒也没用了 只要复制了你 我们就什么都知道了
Tokiko, kill them.
朱鹭子 杀了他们
Father!
爸
Kill them!
快动手
If you kill them, Heine will trust me again.
这样波稻就会重新信任我了
No, Father. You've got it all wrong.
你错了 爸爸 她不会的
They have no intention of keeping their promises.
那些家伙根本没打算遵守 与我们的约定
I'm so disappointed in you, Tokiko.
我对你很失望 朱鹭子
Step back, Sou. Your gun is too close.
快后退 窗 枪离他太近了
Hishigata...
菱形…
What...
什么…
You...
你…
Too bad.
很可惜
Do you think they'll be okay?
小慎他们不会有事吧？
They've got Ushioh and Ms. Nagumo, plus your shadow.
不用担心 有潮姐姐和南云老师跟着 影子泠也在
That's my biggest worry. I still can't trust that thing.
这才是我最担心的 我还没有完全信任她
I'm surprised you let it copy you.
朱鹭子 你竟然愿意让她复制你
When a shadow copies you, it sees your whole body and heart.
被影子复制 身心都会被窥探到吧
Yeah.
嗯
I wanted you to know all of me.
我想让泠更加了解我内心深处的想法
I can't believe you can say that with a straight face!
你竟然能一本正经地说出这种话
I'm done keeping secrets.
因为我不想再有任何隐瞒了
Mioh.
泠
Do you trust me a bit now?
现在对我有多一点信任了吗
Yeah, thanks.
嗯 谢谢你
Really?
真的吗
You can copy me if you don't believe my words.
不相信的话你也可以复制我
Never.
我才不要
I don't want to know what's in your heart.
我又不想知道小慎的内心是怎么想的
Sou.
窗
You shot Tokiko! How could you do that?
竟然对朱鹭子开枪了 你怎么能下得了手
Kill me.
杀了我
You old fool! Playing with people's lives...
混蛋 你把人命当成什么了
Aren't you a doctor?
爸你是医生吧？是吧？
How can a doctor say "kill" so easily? Tell me!
是医生就别随便把杀人放在嘴边啊
So you won't say anything. Fine.
什么都不打算说吗 算了
Mioh, do it.
泠 动手吧
I can't copy him. He has immunity.
无法复制 这个人有免疫
I see. Then he'll need to talk.
是吗 那就只能让他开口…
Wait.
等等
That can't be! You can't copy me?
这不可能 你说无法复制我？
You already had a shadow, but it died.
你的影子被制造出来过 而且那个影子已经死了
People like you have immunity, and you can't be copied again.
这样的人会获得免疫 无法再被复制
It can't be... My shadow can't be created?
不可能 这怎么可能…我已经…
That's what I'm saying.
是的
Doctor...
医生
Chitose, then what did I do everything for?
千登势 那我到底是为了什么…
Negoro.
根来
Doctor, I will be leaving now.
医生 我要回去了
I got what I came for.
首要目的已经达到了
She's beyond my range.
在射程外
Doctor, I have a message from Shide.
四手大人要我传话给你 医生
"We appreciate the Hishigata family for the support you provided."
“一直以来承蒙菱形家的关照了”
"However, it is now over. Take care."
“不过也已经结束了 辛苦你了”
I also have a message for Shinpei Ajiro.
另外还有传给网代慎平的口信
"It seems you didn't die. I am fed up with your stubbornness."
“不知道为什么 但看来你还没死 我已经厌倦了你的纠缠了”
"There's nothing you can do."
“你什么都做不到”
"Everything will end in two days."
“再过两天 这一切就结束了”
Stop! Darn you!
站住 你个混蛋
Don't go!
别去
Don't go after it.
不用追了
But!
可是…
It's using Ushio's body as bait to lure us in.
她想用潮的遗体当诱饵 引我们过去
It brought up the time limit to provoke us.
还故意说了时限 挑衅我们
If we take the bait, we're done.
上当我们就完了
But I can't just let it go, Shinpei. That was the shadow we saw in the hall.
可是慎平 我不甘心 刚才在走廊上看到的影子就是她
Calm down, Sis. Shinpei feels the worst about this.
冷静点 姐姐 最不甘心的人是小慎吧
You can't just let your emotions drive your actions.
冲动行事可不好
Step back from yourself and turn your anger and regret into weapons.
愤怒与不甘在俯瞰过后才能化为武器
Shinpei.
慎平
Dr. Hishigata, does it mean anything for you to keep quiet any longer?
菱形医生 你现在沉默还有意义吗
Get my daughter. Bring me the real Tokiko.
把我女儿…真正的朱鹭子叫来
Are you awake?
你醒了？
W-Where am I?
这里是？
I gave Chitose the same memories I showed you.
和医生一样 我把我的记忆也给千登势阿姨看了
I'm sorry, Chitose.
对不起 千登势
Sou's mother did not realize that she was a shadow herself.
窗的母亲一直不知道自己是影子
She was created that way.
据说一开始就是这么设定的
You are trying to stop the ceremony, but should you really kill Heine?
我知道你们想阻止仪式 但是杀掉波稻真的好吗
What do you mean?
什么意思
All the shadows will die with Heine.
杀了波稻 所有的影子都会死
That means your Ushioh will die too!
也就是说 你的潮也会死
Ushioh.
潮
It's fine! I died two days ago anyway.
没关系 反正我在前天就已经死了
I'm just lucky to have this bonus time being alive.
能活到现在已经很幸运了 像是奖励给我的时间一样
I want to use the time to help save everyone.
如果能用这些时间救大家 我愿意这么做
Defeating Heine will solve everything, right?
打倒波稻一人 就都能解决所有问题了吧？
That's good news! In that case, I'll happily defeat Heine!
听起来是件好事 我很乐意去打倒波稻
She's right. I'm embarrassed that I even hesitated.
也是啊 我为自己有一瞬间的犹豫 感到羞耻
Right?
对吧？
Yeah.
嗯
Dr. Hishigata, what is Heine planning after being revived?
菱形医生 波稻复活后打算做什么
She just wants to go back.
她只是想回去
Back to where she came from, in the deep and dark ocean.
回到遥远的深海彼岸 回到她的故乡
No being from this world can reach that place, unless it's a shadow.
那是这世上的生物无法抵达的地方 只有影子才能前往
Heine wants to just take shadows. Just the family that she chose.
波稻打算只带影子回去 带走她所选择的那个家庭
But that's...
这种事…
It is possible if she regains her power.
是可能的 只要她的力量恢复
It is a land without time.
那里是不存在时间的永恒之国
Chitose and I were going to become shadows and live forever.
我和千登势本来也会变成影子 永远生活在那里
Sou and Tokiko were also supposed to become shadows.
窗和朱鹭子最后也会成为影子
That's why you thought it was okay if you killed us?
所以杀了我们也无所谓吗 你太自私了
Are you a fool? That's the reason?
你是傻瓜吗 就为了这种事？
You're so self-centered and hopeless.
你真是个自私又任性 无可救药的人
Thank you for saving me.
谢谢你救了我
Chitose...
千登势
But we need to finish this. Sou, Tokiko...
不过也该结束了 窗 朱鹭子
I am so glad to have seen you grow until now.
能够看到你们成长 妈妈很开心
No, Chitose. I have no reason to live if you die.
千登势 等等 你要是死了 我活下去还有什么意义
No, you have our children.
不 孩子们还在啊
You have the people of this island who need you.
他们需要你 岛上的人也是
Like Shinpei said, this isn't over.
慎平说得对 还没有结束
You can still make up for your mistakes.
你还能补救这一切 现在开始也不迟
What is this?
这是…
This is the clinic's secret records that Tokiko hid for me.
我让朱鹭子藏起来的 我们医院的秘密病历
Diagnosed with Capgras syndrome, or the local disease of shadow sickness,
诊断结果全都是卡普格拉妄想症 这座岛上的本土病 影子病
the people on this list are actually those whom Heine has consumed.
但实际上 这是那些成为波稻食物的 受害者名单
Your parents' names are on the list, Shinpei.
慎平 这其中也有你父母的名字
They found Hiruko's grotto and planned to make it public.
他们发现了蛭子洞 打算对外公布
That's why they were killed, and the thing made to look like an accident.
所以被杀了 并且伪装成意外
Shide killed them, and I switched the bodies to feed Heine.
是四手下的手 我替换了遗体 并送到了波稻那里去
I'm sorry.
对不起
What? Is that all you have to say?
什么 一句对不起就算了？
You know the true identity of Shide, don't you?
你知道四手的真面目吧？
Yes. Look at this photograph.
嗯 你们看看这张照片
Shide is Heine's protector and the first child she bore.
那家伙是波稻的守护者 也是波稻生下的第一个孩子
The original's name was Shidehiko Hishigata...
原型的名字是菱形纸垂彦
the founder of the Hishigata Clinic and its first director.
菱形医院的创始人 第一任院长